Gladys Edgerly Bates Papers
Gladys Edgerly Bates Papers
1913-1997
Bates, Gladys Edgerly.
2 linear ft.
Papers of the American sculptor, born 1896. Collection includes correspondence (1924-1956); six sketchbooks (1913-1921); photographs of sculpture; a notebook containing an annotated list of works and biographical notes; personal photographs; clippings (1922-1961); and exhibition catalogs (1920s-1961). Notable correspondents include Dolores Bryant, Beatrice Cuming, sister Beatrice Edgerly, Katherine Forest, brother-in-law John Havard MacPherson, Mabel Pugh, Brenda Putnam, Abraham Rattner, Margaret Sanger, Susan Gertrude Schell, and a number of other artists.
148834
Biographical History
Gladys Edgerly Bates (1896- ) was an American sculptor known for her figure carving. She worked in stone, terra-cotta, and wood. Born in Hopewell, New Jersey, she studied at the School of Industrial Arts in Trenton, New Jersey under Henry MacGinnis. In 1910, at MacGinnis' recommendation, she and her younger sister moved to Washington, D.C. to study at the Corcoran School of Art, where they remained for six years until 1916, when both sisters entered the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Art.
In 1923 she married fellow artist Kenneth Bates (1895-1973), a painter known for his landscapes and still lifes. The couple had three children.
Most of Bates' career was spent in Mystic, Connecticut, but her work was exhibited in venues across the country, including the Art Institute of Chicago, Carnegie Institute, and Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York). She was a member of many professional societies including the Mystic Art Association, the National Association of Women Artists, and the National Sculpture Society.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Gladys Edgerly Bates Papers comprises correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the American sculptor. The collection illuminates both her professional and personal career and personal life, as well as, to a lesser extent, that of her husband, painter Kenneth Bates.
Correspondence-subject files (Boxes 1-2) includes incoming family letters from sister Beatrice Edgerly and brother-in-law John Havard Macpherson, both painters, as well as other personal and business communication. Other correspondents include artists (Beonne and Lester Boronda, Clara Bratt, Sheila Burlingame, Doris Caesar, Cornalia Van A. Chapin, Beatrice Cuming, Katherine Forest, Sue May Gill, Genevieve Hamlin, Lucile Howard, Walt Killam, Agnes Lincoln, Arthur Meltzer, Mabel Pugh, Abraham Rattner, Susan Gertrude Schell, Paulette Van Roekens); authors (Faith Andrews, Dolores Bryant, Percy Mackaye); birth control advocate Margaret Sanger; a number of galleries and museums (Art Institute of Chicago, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, Philadelphia Art Alliance, Woodmere Art Gallery); and professional organizations (National Association of Women Artists, National Sculpture Society, Pen and Brush).
Six sketchbooks (1913-1921), photographs of sculpture arranged by title, and a self-generated catalog of Bates' work containing biographical highlights of her career constitute Artwork and Writings (Box 3).
Encompassing personal photographs and printed material, Memorabilia (Box 4) includes photocopies of clippings (1922-1961) from a scrapbook which was disassembled for preservation purposes, and exhibit catalogs.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence-subject files are arranged alphabetically. Artwork, Writings and Memorabila are arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Separated Material
The collection originally contained numerous exhibit catalogs. The bulk of these have been removed from the collection and transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. A copy of Brackman: His Art and Teaching donated in 1997, written by Kenneth Bates and signed/inscribed by Brackman to both Kenneth and Gladys, has also been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Bates, Gladys Edgerly.; Bates, Kenneth, 1895-1973.; Bryant, Dolores Waldorf.; Cuming, Beatrice, 1903-1974.; Edgerly, Beatrice.; Forest, Katherine.; MacPherson, John Havard.; Pugh, Mabel, 1891-1986.; Putnam, Brenda, 1890-1975.; Rattner, Abraham.; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966.; Schell, Susan Gertrude.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Women artists -- United States.; Women sculptors -- United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Sketchbooks.; Artists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Gladys E. Bates, 1965, 1997.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Ames, Winslow, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Andrews, Faith and Jed, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1928-1942 (Box 1)
  - Babcock, Elizabeth Jane, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Boronda, Beonne, 1935-1945 (Box 1)
  - Boronda, Lester, 1943; 1948 (Box 1)
  - Bratt, Clara, 1935; 1948 (Box 1)
  - Braught, Eugenia, 1924-1937; undated (Box 1)
  - Braught, Ross, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Clara H., 1925-1926 (Box 1)
  - Bryant, Dolores Waldorf, 1924-1938 (Box 1)
  - Burlingame, Sheila, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
  - Caesar, Doris, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Institute (Pittsburgh, PA), 1938 (Box 1)
  - Chapin, Cornelia Van A., 1945 (Box 1)
  - Cuming, Beatrice, 1942; undated (Box 1)
  - Edgerly, Beatrice (sister), 1938-1948; 10 folders (Box 1)
  - Edgerly, Beatrice (sister), 1950-1957; undated; 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Forest, Katherine, 1938; 1950,; undated (Box 2)
  - Gill, Sue May, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Hamlin, Genevieve Karr, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Hancock, Walker, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Hatch, Emily Nichols, 1944 (Box 2)
  - Howard, Lucile, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Kelsey, Dorothy, undated (Box 2)
  - Killam, Walt, 1935-1946 (Box 2)
  - Lawton, Alice, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Lincoln, Agnes, 1938; 1942,; 1949 (Box 2)
  - Mackaye, Percy, undated (Box 2)
  - Macpherson, Beatrice Edgerly, See Edgerly, Beatrice (sister)
  - Macpherson, John Havard (brother-in-law), 1940-1956; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Meltzer, Arthur and Paulette Van Roekens, 1925-1926; 1939-1954 (Box 2)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.), 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Miller, Mildred, 1931; undated (Box 2)
  - National Association of Women Artists, 1933-1952 (Box 2)
  - National Association of Women Painters and Sculptors, See National Associaton of Women Artists
  - National Sculpture Society, 1941-1951 (Box 2)
  - State of New Jersey, 1938; 1952-1962 (Box 2)
  - The New Yorker, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Paxton, Elizabeth, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Peabody, Evelyn, 1924 (Box 2)
  - Pen and Brush (New York, N.Y.), 1942-1949 (Box 2)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, 1939-1951 (Box 2)
    See also Memorabilia: Printed Material: School Circular (Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts)
  - Philadelphia Art Alliance, 1936-1950 (Box 2)
  - Price, M. Elizabeth, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Pugh, Mabel, 1924-1951 (Box 2)
  - Putnam, Brenda, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Rattner, Abraham, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Roberts, Lucile Howard, See Howard, Lucile
  - Sanger, Margaret, 1943; 1945 (Box 2)
  - Schell, Susan Gertrude, 1926-1940 (Box 2)
  - Slee, Margaret Sanger, See Sanger, Margaret
  - Southard, Frank Randolph, 1950-1956 (Box 2)
  - Triplett, Margaret L., 1946 (Box 2)
  - Turnbull, Grace H., 1943 (Box 2)
  - Van Roekens, Paulette, See Meltzer, Arthur and Paulette Van Roekens
  - Webb, Elisabeth Holden, 1933-1934; undated (Box 2)
  - Wood, Harrie, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Woodmere Art Gallery (Philadelphia, PA), 1943-1948 (Box 2)
  - A-Z, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Artwork
  - Original
    - Sketchbooks, 1913-1921; 6 books (Box 3)
  - Reproductions
    - Photographs by title, A-Z, 4 folders (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Catalog of Bates' work, biographical highlights (Box 3)
  - Poems (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Kenneth Bates catalog of paintings, handwritten sheets in small 3-ring binder (Box 4)
  - Photographs, personal, studio, residence, exhibitions (Box 4)
  - Printed material
    - Clippings, 1922-1961 (Box 4)
    - Exhibition catalogs, 1920s-1960s; 5 folders (Box 4)
      Most of the exhibit catalogs have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
    - Exhibition catalogs, joint shows with Kenneth, 1961; 1985 (Box 4)
    - School circular, Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, 1916-1924; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Who's Who listing, 1983; 1997; photocopies of entries for Gladys and Kenneth (Box 4)